Guide to the Sergei Gornyi (Aleksandr Otsup) Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Sergei Gornyi (Aleksandr Otsup) Papers,
1923-1948.
Gornyĭ, Sergi︠e︡ĭ, 1882-1949
2.5 linear ft. (5 document boxes)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY. 10027
BA#0533
9025420
The papers comprise correspondence, writings, personal documents, biographical materials, and photographs of Sergei Gornyi (Aleksandr Otsup), 1882-1948, Russian poet and writer.
Biographical Note
Sergei Gornyi (pseudonym of Aleksandr-Mark Avdeevich Otsup), Russian poet and writer, was born on July 28, 1882 in Ostrov, Pskov Region. He was an older brother of poets Nikolai Otsup and Georgii Otsup (pen name G. Raevskii).
Sergei Gornyi graduated with a gold medal from the Nikolaev Gymnasium in Tsarskoe Selo and then in 1908 from the Institute of Mining in Saint-Petersburg. He started publishing his works in satirical publications in 1906. In 1911, Gornyi's first book with satirical short stories was published. His feuilletons, parodies, and poetry appeared in Satirikon, Novyi Satiricon, and many other publications.
After graduation, Gornyi and his wife moved to Ekaterinoslav where he started a successful career as an entrepreneur. After the revolution of 1917, Gornyi moved to Kiev, and then to Odessa. In 1919, he served in Denikin's army, was wounded and captured by Makhnovtsy. In 1920, Gornyi was evacuated from Novorossiisk to Cyprus and in 1922 moved to Berlin. In emigration, Sergei Gornyi wrote prose and poetry, publishing books in Russian and German. His writings were published in Russian emigre, German, French, and Spanish periodicals. After World War II, he published two collections of short stories and a collection of poetry in German. Sergei Gornyi died on September 16, 1948 in Madrid and was buried there.
Scope and Content
The bulk of the collection consists of Sergei Gornyi's correspondence and his writings. There are also personal documents, biographical materials, reviews and critiques of his prose and poetry, a few photographs, letters addressed to his wife Ekaterina Nikolaevna Otsup, and her memoirs.
Sergei Gornyi's and Ekaterina Otsup's correspondence contains letters from several prominent people, such as Maria Hippius, Ivan Aleksandrovich Il'in, Arthur Luther, Ivan Ivanovich Manukhin, Nikolai Otsup, Elena Sergeevna Pil'skaia, Nadezhda Aleksandrovna Teffi.
The collection contains manuscripts of Gornyi's writings as well as his printed works.
There are cross-references provided throughout the finding aid. When the cross-reference refers to another item within the same series, the reference includes the specific name or title and box and folder number (this also applies to the references within same subseries). If the cross-reference is to an item in another series, the reference includes the series number, series name, folder title, and box and folder numbers (this also applies to references to the items in another subseries).
Arrangement
This collection is organized in five series:
Series I: Correspondence, 1941-1955
Subseries I.1: Gorny's Correspondence, 1941-1949
Subseries I.2: Letters to Ekaterina Nikolaevna Otsup, 1948-1955
Series II: Writings by Sergei Gornyi, undated, 1940s
Subseries II.1: Manuscripts, undated, 1945
Subseries II.2: Printed Materials, 1914-1966
Series III: Biographical Materials, Bibliography, and Reviews, 1923-1948
Subseries III.1: Biographical Materials and Bibliography, 1926-1948
Subseries III.2: Reviews, 1923-1948
Series IV: Photographs, 1926-1948
Series V: Writings by Others, undated, 1945
Subjects
Gornyĭ, Sergi︠e︡ĭ, 1882-1949.; Il'in, I. A. (Ivan Aleksandrovich), 1883-1954.; Luther, Arthur, 1876-1955.; Manukhin, Ivan Ivanovich, b. 1882.; Otsup, Nikolai, 1894-1958.; Pil'skaia, Elena Sergeevna.; Teffi, N. A. (Nadezhda Aleksandrovna), 1872-1952.; Russian literature--20th century.; Russian literature--Germany--20th century.; Correspondence.; Manuscripts.; Memoirs.; Photographs.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located on-site.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
Gornyi Family Gift 1997 December
- Series I: Correspondence, 1941-1955
  The series consists of Sergei Gornyi's correspondence and letters to Ekaterina Nikolaevna Otsup and includes letters from several prominent figures. Organized in two subseries.
  - Subseries I.1: Gornyi's correspondence, 1941-1949
    Contains letters to Sergei Gornyi from various people (including letters from readers), correspondence with publishers, and outgoing letters including Gornyi's letters to his daughter. Arranged alphabetically. Unidentified, outgoing correspondence, and correspondence with publishers placed at the end of the Subseries.
    - Albers, Margarethe, Reinbek, 1947-1948, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Auerbuch, V., Brussels, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Benz, Elly, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Diudan, Elena, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Gaudecker, Rita von, 1948, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Gunther, Erich, Goslar, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Hippius, Maria, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Hopner, Ermano, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      (including typescript of his article. See also Correspondence with Publishers, Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Il'in, Ivan Aleksandrovich, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Kempe, Richard, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Lampe, Aleksei Aleksandrovich, von, undated. Letter to Colonel Franco (Box 1, Folder 5)
      (typescript copy)
    - Luther, Arthur, Marburg, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Ofrosimov, Iu., 1947 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Otsup, Mikhail, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Pil'skaia, Elena, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Ramle, Edith, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Rewendt, Margot, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Schoen, R., 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Schroter, Erich, 1946-1948 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      (including 1 letter to Gornyi's daughter Liudmila)
    - Senitskaia, Lidiia, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      (including manuscript of her poem dedicated to S.Gornyi)
    - Shiriaeva, Mariia, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Shtegman, O., 1947 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Spengler, Helga, Hannover, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Wandschneider, Goslar, 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Wittenstein, Geni, Stuttgart, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Unidentified, 1945-1948 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Outgoing letters:
      - To his daughter, 1946-1947, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
        (including manuscripts of S.Gornyi poems)
      - To unidentified, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence with Publishers, 1941-1949 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      (including advertisements and reviews)
  - Subseries I.2: Letters to Ekaterina Nikolaevna Otsup, 1948-1955
    Comprises mostly letters of condolences. Organized in alphabetical order.
    - Hopner, Ermano, Hamburg, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Kvak, Emiliia Andreevna, Barcelona, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Manukhin, Ivan Ivanovich, Paris, 1948-1953 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Otsup, Diana, [1948], undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Otsup, Georgii (aka Georgii Raevskii), [1948] (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Otsup, Nikolai, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Otsup, Sergei, Madrid, 1948, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      (1 letter addressed to Arthur Luther; 1 - to Ekaterina Otsup)
    - Tėffi, N. A. (Nadezhda Aleksandrovna), Paris, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Series II: Writings, undated, 1940s
  The series comprises manuscripts of Sergei Gornyi's literary works and printed writings. Arranged in two subseries.
  - Subseries II.1: Manuscripts, undated, 1945
    Holograph manuscripts and typescripts of prose (short stories and essays), poetry, and plays in Russian, German, and Spanish. There are also some diary entries of unspecified year in the notebook with manuscripts. Materials organized in several groups - prose, poetry, plays, and diaries - and then arranged by language within each of them. Collection of writing that includes both poetry and prose are placed at the beginning of the Subseries.
    - Prose (short stories and essays)
      - In Russian:
        - Collection of short stories and poetry, undated, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 20 to 22)
          (contain some diary entries. Manuscripts in three bound notebooks)
        - "Antinoi" (Box 1, Folder 23)
        - "Aleksei Shiriaev" (Box 1, Folder 24)
        - "Begstvo" (Box 1, Folder 25)
        - "Gaudeamus Igitur" (Box 1, Folder 26 to 28)
        - "Inseparables" (Box 2, Folder 1)
        - "'Itogi' Shaliapina" (Box 2, Folder 2)
        - "Kopeliia" (Box 2, Folder 3)
        - "Lileia" (Box 2, Folder 4)
        - "Mertvoi khvatkoi" (Box 2, Folder 5)
        - "Mikhasia zarezali" (Box 2, Folder 6)
        - "Momental'nyi snimok" (Box 2, Folder 7)
        - "Parnas na Neve" (Box 2, Folder 8)
        - "Peri" (Box 2, Folder 9)
        - "Pestryi platok" (Box 2, Folder 10)
        - "Pochemu vy ne progonite Lushu?" (Box 2, Folder 11)
        - "Roman v pis'makh 'Dzhiovanna'" (Box 2, Folder 12)
        - "Sosedi" (Box 2, Folder 13)
        - "Strakh" (Box 2, Folder 14)
        - "Tauschzentrale" (Box 2, Folder 15)
        - "Tri vystrela" (Box 2, Folder 16)
        - "V3-V5-V7" (Box 2, Folder 17)
        - "V sinei kolybeli" (Box 2, Folder 18)
        - "V sumerki" (Box 2, Folder 19)
        - "Vashi pal'tsy pakhnut ladanom" (Box 2, Folder 20)
        - "Videniia" (Box 2, Folder 21)
        - Untitled (Box 2, Folder 22)
      - In German:
        - "Atomzertrummerung" (Box 2, Folder 23)
        - "Drei Miniaturen" (Box 2, Folder 24)
        - "Geopolitik" (Box 2, Folder 25)
        - "Kuka" (Box 2, Folder 26)
        - "Unwiderstehliche" (Box 2, Folder 27)
        - "Vor der Kolner Dom" (Box 2, Folder 28)
      - In Spanish:
        - "Revolucion Silenciosa" (Box 2, Folder 29)
        - "Suenos" (Box 2, Folder 30)
        - "Tres Disparos" (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Poetry (see also notebooks in Box 1, Folders 21-22)
      - In Russian:
        - Various poems (Box 2, Folder 32 to 34)
        - "Dusha bukv" (Box 2, Folder 35)
          (manuscript, one original illustration, foreword by Peter Posse)
        - Translations of Rainer Maria Rilke poetry and Gornyi's poetry in the style of Rilke (Box 2, Folder 36)
      - In German (Box 2, Folder 37 to 39)
    - Plays:
      - "Regreso", Madrid, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 1)
        (in collaboration with Alejandro Botzaris. Bound carbon copy of typescript in Spanish)
      - "Regreso" (Box 3, Folder 2)
        (selected acts in Russian)
    - Diaries: some diary entries of unspecified year are in the notebook with manuscripts in Box 1, Folder 22
  - Subseries II.2: Printed Materials, 1914-1966
    Books by S. Gornyi and periodicals with his publications in Russian and German.
    - In Russian:
      - Iantarnyi Kipr. Berlin: Mysl', 1922 (2 copies) (Box 3)
      - Pochti bez ulybki: Paradoksy. Siluety. S.-Peterburg: Novyi Satirikon, 1914 (Box 3)
      - Poety "Satirikona" Moskva, Leningrad: Sovetskii pisatel', 1966 (Box 3)
      - Pugachev ili Petr? (Dusha naroda) Berlin: Otto Kirkhner i Ko., 1922 (Box 3)
      - Rannei vesnoi Berlin: Parabola (Box 3)
        (2 copies. 1 copy is with S. Gornyi's inscription to Arthur Luther dated September 17, 1932)
      - Sankt-Peterburg (Vidieniia) Munkhen: Izdatel'stvo Milavida (Box 3)
      - Tol'ko o veshchakh Petropolis (2 copies. 1 copy is with author's inscription to Mariia Sergeevna dated January 30, 1938) (Box 3)
      - Vsiakoe byvalo Berlin: Izdatel'stvo pisatelei, 1927 (2 copies) (Box 3)
    - In German:
      - "Brief an einen Toten" in Erzahler aus aller Welt Flensburg und Hamburg: Verlagshaus Christian Wolff (2 copies) (Box 4)
      - "Dorf: Balknewande Kalte Wasser Duftende Graser. Kann Man es Vergessen?", Berlin, 1923 (photocopy) (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - "Drei Pistolenschusse" in Karussell: Literarische Monatsschrift, Januar 1947 Folge 7 (Box 4)
      - "Lilie" " in Karussell: Literarische Monatsschrift, September 1947 Folge 15 (Box 4)
      - "Macht der Dinge" in Schweizer Journal: Review Suisse Dez. 1941 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - Mit Leisen Schritten Harriet Schleber Verlag Kassel (2 copies) (Box 4)
      - "Peri" in Karussell: Literarische Monatsschrift June 1947 Folge 12 (Box 4)
      - Schattentraum Baden-Baden: Verlag Hans Buhler Junior, 1947 (Box 4)
      - Sein Leben in Erzahler aus aller Welt. Flensburg und Hamburg: Verlagshaus Christian Wolff (2 copies) (Box 4)
      - Susse Gewohnheit des Daseins. Christian Wolff Verlag (Box 4)
    - Clippings, various years (Box 4, Folder 3)
      (publications in Russian and German. Arranged alphabetically)
- Series III: Biographical Materials, Bibliography, and Reviews, 1923-1948
  This series arranged in two Subseries.
  - Subseries III.1: Biographical Materials and Bibliography, 1926-1948
    The Subseries contains Gornyi's autobiographies, CVs, testimonials on his behalf by various people, personal documents, bibliography and other biographical materials.
    - Autobiographies and CVs, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Testimonials on behalf of Sergei Gornyi, 1943-1946 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Personal documents:
      - Passport, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 3)
      - Membership card of the Tsentral'nyi soiuz uvechnykh voinov v Germanii, gor. Berlin, 1926 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Materials related to S. Gorny's death: obituaries, articles, memorial cards, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Various, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Bibliography, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Subseries III.2: Reviews, 1923-1948
    Contains reviews of Sergei Gornyi's writings from Russian, German, French, and Spanish press. See also Series 1: Correspondence--Correspondence with Publishers, Box 1, Folder 15
    - Reviews in Russian press, 1923-1927, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Reviews in Russian press, 1930s (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Reviews in German, French, and Spanish, 1933-1948 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Series IV: Photographs, 1926-1948
  There is a photograph of Rita von Gaudecker and funeral photograph of Sergei Gornyi (his photo on the Membership card of 1926 is stored along with his personal documents in Series III--Subseries III.1: Biographical Materials).
  - Gaudecker, Rita von, undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Gornyi, Serge
    - Photo on the Membership card, Berlin, 1926 see Series III--Subseries III.1: Biographical Materials (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Photo in a coffin, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 10)
      (two black and white prints)
- Series V: Writings by Others, undated, 1945
  The series includes memoirs of Ekaterina Otsup and writings by various authors sent to S. Gornyi for critique.
  - Otsup, Ekaterina. "Moi vospominaniia", undated (Box 5, Folder 11 to 12)
    (manuscript in 2 notebooks)
  - Senitskaia, Lidiia. "To S. Gornyi", 1947 (poem, holograph manuscript): see Series I: Correspondence--Gornyi's Correspondence--Senitskaia (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Writings by various authors sent to S. Gornyi for critique, 1945, undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
    (In German)